Hello English learners
welcome back to English pod
my name is Marco and my
name is Catherine and today
I think we're hitting
the gym at Marco.
We need to be healthy. We've
gained weight over the winter
I think I think so and being
in an office, you know, it
doesn't give you much opportunity
to go and exercise and really
Get a lot of work exactly so that's why
we're going to the gym on this occasion
We're gonna be pumping some
iron. We're gonna be working out.
So why don't we take a look at
vocabulary. We can't see what this means
vocabulary preview
All right, so to pump
iron what does that mean?
All right, well to pumping
iron means lifting weights.
Okay, so we're pumping
iron. We're lifting weights
You know weights are made of
iron right to make them so heavy
All right, so we're
pumping iron good and well,
we're gonna be giving
you guys some pointers
All right, so you might
have heard the word point
before well pointers
is another word for tips
All right, so we're gonna
be giving you tips or advice.
Yep, so you're gonna get
some help today from the trainer
All right, so we're gonna
jump right into this dialogue
and we come back. We're
talking more about what's going on
Hey there you look a little lost.
Are you new here?
Yeah, how did you know?
You can always spot the
newbies. I can give you a few
pointers if you want. Will you
try to use this machine here?
Yeah, I just lost my train today,
and I'm not sure where to begin
It's okay. I know how it is this machine
here will work out your upper body
Mainly your triceps and
biceps. Are you looking
to develop strength or
muscle tone and definition?
Well, I don't want
to be ripped like you.
I just want a good physique
with weights and cardio
In that case you want to
work with the last weight you
can start off by working
10 to 15 reps and four sets
Five kilowatt should be enough
now. It's very important that
you stretch before pumping
iron. You might pull a muscle
Got it. Wow. Is that the weight you're
lifting my goodness? That's means of weight
It's not that much just watch
Okay
So this guy was a little bit arrogant.
I think he was very you know very muscular
But I think he embarrassed
himself in front of the lady the trainer
you mean yeah, yeah,
definitely so he he we say he
had a big ego Yeah, he
thought a lot about himself
So let's check out some of
these phrases and words they were
using because they're they're
all related to going at the gym
And they can help you if you ever want
to get some help when you're at the gym
So this girl she was new in the gym
She didn't really know what she
was doing and well the guy said well
Do you want to develop
strength or muscle tone?
All right, we know it's strength
is but what is muscle tone?
Okay, so if you want
to develop muscle tone
or to have muscle tone
it means that you have
Healthy muscles not like huge big
muscles, right? But you have a nice body
Right, so tone to tone is to maybe make
give some shape to something you know
Sometimes you have big arms and they're
not really that you can't see the muscles
Well muscle tone means
that you can start to see
the shape and they start
to get stronger all right
So you think of Madonna
maybe five years ago.
She had a lot of muscle
tone now. She's like
Big muscle is strong but
muscle tone means that
you can see the muscles.
They start to develop
Okay, and this actually
is very related to
our next word because
you said muscle tone and
Definition right so definition is
another way for us to describe
Seeing those muscles
because at first you have a big
tummy or you have big arms
and when you start to work out
Every time you go you can
see more and more definition
that means more and more
of the muscle becomes visible
All right, so you have defined muscles.
All right good now the girl was like no
I don't want to be like
super strong and huge right
doesn't want to look like Arnold
Schwarzenegger Yeah, exactly.
She said I just want
a good physique.
All right, this word may be sound
strange for some of you because it
Sounds French more like French
than English. Yeah, well, it does
come from French and physique is
a way to talk about the whole body
You know the physique is the
The state of your whole body. It's your
physical appearance. Okay, so I can say
She has a nice physique
So that means she's
probably works out a lot
So but basically it's like her
whole body right and you can't
just say like she's she
has good physique in
her arms or something
And now you're physique
Physical thing of the word physical. It's
your whole body your whole body. All right
So good physique and now the tips
that he was giving her or the pointers
He was talking about these
two words reps and sets
Right, these are great
words for the gym because
they they allow us to count
when we're working out
So the first one is reps or repetitions.
I mean doing something over and over again
So for example, if I want to lift a weight
I sit down the bench. I do one
Two three how many times I lift that
weight is a repetition or a rep all right
And well, and what about sets?
So I could say I lift the weight ten times
One two three four all the way to ten
And then I wait and then I do it again. So
the number of times. I do it again is a set
So sets of ten or sets of five. Okay, so
if you are lifting this weight ten times
And you have five sets
you will do a total of
50 pushes or
Yeah repetitions. Okay, so
reps and sets are probably
the most important or common
words you'll hear in the gym
Especially if you're
lifting weights, right?
Mm-hmm definitely and sometimes
your trainer will count with you
So that he'll he'll keep the
count while you're working out
Cool, so those are the words that we
have for you on language take away
I think in order to better
understand these words
We should listen to our dialogue again, but
we're gonna slow it down just a little bit
Hey there, you look a little lost.
Are you new here?
Yeah, how did you know?
You can always spot the newbies.
I can give you a few pointers if you want
Were you trying to use this machine here?
Yeah, I just started my training today.
I'm not really sure where to begin
It's okay. I know how it is
This machine here will
work out your upper body
Mainly your triceps and
biceps. Are you looking
to develop strength or
muscle tone and definition?
Well, I don't want
to be ripped like you.
I just want a good physique
with weights and cardio
In that case you want
to work with less weight
You can start off by working
10 to 15 reps in four sets
Five kilo weights should be enough
Now, it's very important
that you stretch
before pumping iron or
you might pull a muscle
Got it. Wow. Is that
the weight you're lifting?
My goodness.
That's a lot of weight
It's not that much just watch
I'm okay
All right, so you might
have heard some other
phrases in there that sound
interesting or new to you
And that's where we're going to go
into the fluency builder part of lesson.
We can talk about sounding
more fluent in English
Fluency builder All right, so
the girl she was a little bit lost
right so this guy was trying to help her
out I think it was her first time in the gym
It was and and she doesn't
really know where to start
Which is a common problem for
people who go to the gym for the first time
So the guy said well, um, yeah,
I know how it is. How what is
Exactly how it is strange phrase
because it's vague. It's not clear
So what is he referring
to? There's something
very common that we
say in English to mean
I understand your situation.
I know how you feel. I know how you feel so
She says this is my first time.
I don't know what to do and he says
I know how it is. I
understand your situation
because I imagine the first
time he went to the gym
He felt the same way exactly I could say
I'm so lost. I'm
new at this school.
I don't even know anyone.
Yeah, I know how it is
I was new here last year.
So trust me. I know how it is.
Okay, so Marco and I have
similar situations although he
Has already experienced
that so he can help me out.
This is a good
phrase. It's actually
I think it's very common for
somebody to kind of sympathize with you
Absolutely, and it's a
really good phrase if you
want to help someone
who looks lost or confused
So if someone joins your your
work, I knew if you have a new
colleague and I say oh, I
don't know where anything
is. I don't know how this
how to do anything at my job
You say oh, I know how it is right.
I was known here last month
Great and well now they were talking about
you know lifting weights in the physique
And she said this interesting where
she says I don't want to be ripped like you
Okay, so many of you have
probably heard the other meaning
of the word to rip right
or ripped. So this is to rip
Yeah, to tear but in this
case, it's an adjective.
It's a way to describe
someone's physique their body
And we're talking about people
who are very very muscular.
Okay, so basically bodybuilders
Arnold Schwarzenegger is ripped.
He has ripped huge muscles
Madonna is ripped. She has
huge muscles. Okay, so it's a
very informal way But it's a
very informal way of saying
Very muscular.
Yeah, it's someone who works out a lot
All right, you're ripped and after
this we've got one more phrase
It's actually very important because when
we talk about going to the gym working out
We have to talk about
safety and your health as well.
It's very easy to hurt yourself
Right, and that's what we want to avoid.
You don't want to pull a muscle
All right, pull a muscle. This is a key
phrase here because we have a special
Combination of verb and now
the thing that we pull is our muscle
And what we do to it is we
pull it that means we hurt it
So if you don't stretch and
your lifting weights, maybe
your muscle will start to
hurt and you can't lift anymore
Yeah, you you hurt it. You pulled your
muscle or often runners have this problem
They don't stretch before
they run or they run too
much and they have a
lot of pain in their muscles
You say I pulled a muscle.
Mm-hmm. Now. I think there's
another way of saying it also
is to to tear a muscle, right?
Tear is more serious a
tear is like a little rip in your
muscle and you should
really see a doctor about that
Okay, so we don't want you to
pull a muscle or to tear a muscle
So be sure to stretch but
we have some more examples
with this phrase to pull
a muscle. So let's listen
Example one
Muscle strains also call pull
muscles are common sports injuries
Example two
If you do not warm up before physical
activity, you can easily pull a muscle
Example three
Anyone can pull a muscle because of
overuse muscle fatigue or through a fall
All right, so now that that's
clear I think we can listen to
our gym dialogue one more
time and see what happens to this
Eric and body doing absolutely
Hey there, you look a little lost.
Are you new here?
Yeah, how did you know?
You can always spot the
newbies. I can give you a few
pointers if you want. Will you
try to use this machine here?
Yeah, I just started my training
today, and I'm not sure where to begin
It's okay. I know how it is this machine
here will work out your upper body
Mainly your triceps and
biceps. Are you looking
to develop strength or
muscle tone and definition?
Well, I don't want to be ripped like you
I just want a good physique with
weights and cardio in that case
You want to work with
the last weight you can
start off by working 10
to 15 reps and four sets
Five kilowatt should be enough
now. It's very important that
you stretch before pumping
iron. You might pull a muscle
Got it. Wow. Is that the weight you're
lifting my goodness? That sounds a waste
It's not that much. Just watch
Okay
All right, Catherine. So
we know that you are
a very healthy person.
You often go to the gym
This is true. I like
to go to the gym.
So any any gym stories. Oh,
gosh, I have lots of gym stories
I like to run and I often
use the treadmill and
And I've never really understood
the people who don't run on
the treadmill people who stand
or who walk on the treadmill
And I remember my gym
is usually very crowded
I remember one time I
was at my gym and I wanted
to run on the treadmill.
I had a long day at work
And I had to go out afterwards. So I
didn't have much time. I only had an hour
And I really wanted
to run, but there's a line
for the treadmills. There
are too many people
And this particular day I was
waiting and waiting and waiting and
finally was my turn and I stepped
and a woman cut and fronted me
No, she cut and fronted me and I
was so angry and what did she do?
In her heels heels big shoes.
She walked for 40 minutes.
Oh my god. You could go
outside and walk. I want to run
But she was wearing heels at the gym in
her heels at the gym. Wow. Well, I guess
You have to look nice when
you go to the gym. Apparently.
Well, it is a very popular place for a
people to meet right to start dating
They say after the office
the gym is one of the most
Common places for people to
meet their boyfriends and girlfriends.
Wow. So there's another good reason
why you should go to the gym Absolutely.
Yeah, all right. So that's all
the time we have for today
But we would like to hear if
you have any questions any
doubts or comments so come
to our site EnglishPod.com
And if you have any gym
stories, we'd also like to hear those
So that's gonna do it for us
until next time everyone. Bye. Bye